Leon Kelly Papers
Leon Kelly Papers
1882-1965
Kelly, Leon, 1901-1982.
3.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter, muralist. Correspondence (1938-1965); manuscripts and other material relating to Kelly's work and family history; photographs of work and family; and published material, including articles about Kelly, clippings, and exhibition announcements and catalogs.
149099
Biographical History
Leon Kelly (1901-1982) was an American surrealist painter. In his manuscript of the history of the Kelly family, Leon Kelly states that he was born in Perignan, France. His father, however, persuaded the family physician in Philadelphia to have the birth recorded as having taken place there. As a child, Kelly studied art privately then at the Pennsylvania Academy of Art (1921-1924), and maintained a studio in France for several years until 1930. He taught art at the Brooklyn Museum and the University of Wyoming, and his work was exhibited at, and is in the permanent collections of, many of the great galleries both in the United States and abroad. He is remembered as a significant artist of the American surrealist movement.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Leon Kelly Papers contains correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, photographs, and published material. Correspondence includes galleries, museums and academic institutions as well as other artists. Notable correspondents include Isabel Bishop, Lucien Cailliet, Massimo Campigli, Minna Citron, Félix Fénéon, Dorothy Hood, Benjamin Kopman, Julien Levy, Adrian and Sophie Siegel, Marcel Tabuteau, Yves Tanguy, Alice B. Toklas, Glenway Wescott, and Carl Zigrosser. Subject files includes passports, tax returns, and lists of exhibits, mailings, paintings and prices. Manuscripts consists of writings about Kelly, by himself and by others, and a Kelly family history. Photographs contains photographs of Kelly's work as well as some personal photos. Published material consist of articles about Kelly, exhibit notices, clippings about Kelly, and clippings about others.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is divided into incoming (arranged alphabetically by sender) and outgoing (arranged chronologically). Subject files, manuscripts, photographs, and published material are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Bishop, Isabel, 1902-1988.; Cailliet, Lucien, 1891-1985.; Campigli, Massimo, 1895-1971.; Citron, Minna, 1896-1991.; Fénéon, Félix, 1861-1944.; Hood, Dorothy, 1919-; Kelly, Leon, 1901-1982.; Kopman, Benjamin, 1887-; Siegel, Adrian.; Siegel, Sophie.; Tabuteau, Marcel, 1887-1966.; Tanguy, Yves, 1900-1955.; Toklas, Alice B.; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987.; Zigrosser, Carl, 1891-1975.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Mural painting and decoration -- United States -- 20th century.; Mural painting and decoration, American.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical Material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - A-C (Box 1)
    - Art Institute of Chicago (Box 1)
    - Ash, Isaac (Box 1)
    - Barbara, George, 1961; 1962,; 1965,; undated (Box 1)
    - The Barnes Affair (Box 1)
    - Bayne, Walter and Lucy (Box 1)
    - Benedict, Walter, 1960; 1963,; 1965,; undated (Box 1)
    - Berman, Eugene (Box 1)
    - Bishop, Isabel (Box 1)
    - Blodgett, George W. (Box 1)
    - Bok, Mrs. Curtis (Box 1)
    - Brody, Sol, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - Caillet, Lucien (Box 1)
    - Caillet, Marcel (Box 1)
    - Campigli, Massimo (Box 1)
    - Carnegie Institute (Box 1)
    - Carton, Norman (Box 1)
    - Ciani, Vladimoro (Box 1)
    - Citron, Minna (Box 1)
    - Clevenger, E. H. (Box 1)
    - Committee on International Exchange of Persons (Box 1)
    - Cuadra, Ricardo (Box 1)
    - D-G (Box 1)
    - Dallam, John (Box 1)
    - De Beausaeq, Contesse I. (Box 1)
    - Di Rosa, Rene (Box 1)
    - Drabkin, David and Stella (Box 1)
    - Ermilio, Michael and Lenore (Box 1)
    - Etting, Emlen and Gloria (Box 1)
    - Fénéon, Mme and Monsieur Félix (Box 1)
    - Freid, Sam (Box 1)
    - Georgian Court College Students and Faculty, 1960; 1962,; 1963,; undated (Box 1)
    - Soleman R. Guggenheim Museum (Box 1)
    - H-L (Box 1A)
    - Hagendorn, Ruth (Box 1A)
    - Hayter, Stanley William, undated (Box 1A)
    - Herndon, Venable and Ursule (Box 1A)
    - Hinchman, Margaretta (Box 1A)
    - Hogue, Bob (Box 1A)
    - Holburn, Gerd (Box 1A)
    - Honig, Ethelynn (Box 1A)
    - Hood, Dorothy, 1962-1965; undated (Box 1A)
    - Howard, Morton (Box 1A)
    - Hubbard, Betty Paul (Box 1A)
    - Iolas Gallery, 1955; 1958-1959,; 1964 (Box 1A)
    - Kelly, Mrs. Elizabeth (mother) (Box 1A)
    - Kelly, Helen, 1950-1952; 1960,; 1962-1964 (Box 1A)
    - Kelly, Henriette, 1938-1939; undated (Box 1A)
    - Kelly, Panteleon L. (father) (Box 1A)
    - Kelly, Paula, 1950's; 1960,; 1962,; 1964,; 1965,; undated (Box 1A)
    - Kevorkian, John, 1960; undated (Box 1A)
    - Kopman, Ben (Box 1A)
    - Kulicke, Frames, Inc., 1959-1961; 1964 (Box 1A)
    - Lefebvre-Foinet, Lucien (Box 2)
    - Leuy, Berna and Douglas (Box 2)
    - Levy, Julien, 1940-1950; 1959-1961,; undated (Box 2)
    - Lodge, John Davis, 1960 (Box 2)
    - M-R (Box 2)
    - Mackey, William (Box 2)
    - Marine Corps (Box 2)
    - McNulty, Father P. J. (Box 2)
    - Museum of Modern Art (Box 2)
    - National Gallery of Art (Box 2)
    - Newport, Ike (Box 2)
    - Nichols, Inez (Box 2)
    - Noble, Janet, 1960-1963; undated (Box 2)
    - Oppenheimer, Robert (Box 2)
    - Park, Paul (Box 2)
    - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, 1961; 1963-1964,; undated (Box 2)
    - Pennsylvania Museum of Art (Box 2)
    - Pepp, Claire (Box 2)
    - Perakis, Petros (Box 2)
    - Philadelphia Art Alliance (Box 2)
    - Philadelphia Museum of Art (Box 2)
    - Reynal, Jeanne (Box 2)
    - Rosa Angela, Sister (cousin) (Box 2)
    - S-Z (Box 2)
    - Shapiro, Edwin A., 1959-1962 (Box 2A)
    - Siegal, Adrian and Sophie (Box 2A)
    - Tabuteau, Marcel and Louise (Box 2A)
    - Tai (Box 2A)
    - Tanguy, Yves and Kay (Box 2A)
    - Toklas, Alice (Box 2A)
    - Tyson, Carroll and Helen (Box 2A)
    - View Magazine (Box 2A)
    - Vilary, Lenore (Box 2A)
    - Voelker, Curt and Kathe (Box 2A)
    - Volodine, George (Box 2A)
    - Waas, Milton J. (Box 2A)
    - Warren, Liz and Dick (Box 2A)
    - Welch, Harriett (Box 2A)
    - Wescott, Glenway (Box 2A)
    - White, Vera (Box 2A)
    - Whitney Museum (Box 2A)
    - Whitney Museum, 1962 (Box 2A)
    - Woodward, Shirley & Stanley Sr. (Box 2A)
    - Woodward, Stanley Jr., 1947-1948; 1952,; 1958,; 1960-1961,; undated (Box 2A)
    - Woolley, Louise D., 1962-1964 (Box 2A)
    - Zabriskie Gallery, 1963 (Box 2A)
    - Zeid, Princess Fahr El Nissa, 1960 (Box 2A)
    - Zygrosser, Carl (Box 2A)
    - Not Identifiable (Box 2A)
  - Correspondence of others
    - Kelly, Mrs. Elizabeth (mother) (Box 2A)
    - Kelly, Mrs. Helen (wife) (Box 2A)
  - Outgoing
    - 1941, 1945-1947, 1950-1951, 1957-1965, undated (Box 2A)
- Subject files
  - Account Book (Box 3)
  - Divorce (Box 3)
  - Documents and Passports (Box 3)
  - Edwin Hewitt Gallery, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Hugo Gallery (Box 3)
  - Income Tax Returns, 1941-1959 (Box 3)
  - Iolas Gallery (Box 3)
  - Paula Kelly (Box 3)
  - Julien Levy Collection (Box 3)
  - List - Exhibitions (Box 3)
  - Lists - Mailing (Box 3)
  - Lists - Paintings (Box 3)
  - Lists - Prices (Box 3)
  - Retrospective Exhibit, 1956 (Box 3)
- Manuscripts
  - About Kelly by Others (Box 4)
  - Explication of Kelly's Work by Kelly (Box 4)
  - Family History (Box 4)
  - Notes on Painting (Box 4)
  - Notes on Painting, Techniques, Materials (Box 4)
  - Of Others (Box 4)
  - Plan for an Art Gallery (Box 4)
- Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 4)
  - Family, Friends, and Self (Box 4)
  - Kelly's Work (Box 4)
  - Kelly's Work - Negatives (Box 4)
  - Unidentifiable (Box 4)
- Published material
  - Articles About Kelly (Box 4)
  - Exhibit Notices (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings About Kelly (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings About Others (Box 4)